Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): Driving stick is just fun. You have to be smooth and maintain positions and pedal pressure. If it seems wrong, it probably
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): is. If you whip on and off the gas, let's see if I can do it. Oh
yeah, there
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): it is. Oh god.
what's going on people I
Speaker 3: thought I would do a revised
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): video on how to drive a stick shift or especially just good tips
Speaker 4: relating
to that
So,
Speaker 4: today I'm driving my 1984 Porsche 944. It's just a great old little sports car, one that's super reliable, and I just enjoy having. It's kind
Man 5: of a everyday classic. Obviously a five-speed manual gearbox,
very,
Man 5: basic bare-bones sports car. And my first video I did a year ago was also in a 944. That was a red one, but this particular one happens to be the one I've always wanted with the rare color combination. You guys can see the wacky Porsche Pasha fabric and
Speaker 6 (lower-pitched voice): I've got this fluffy seat cover because it's winter and cold. But let's go for a drive and just talk about this. I think this is gonna be helpful for young people and for all the Europeans that are going to
Speaker 4: be snarky right now and going, "I'm not gonna take shifting advice from a Yank."
Speaker 4: or an American. Okay, down.
Anyway, all
Speaker 6 (lower-pitched voice): right, guys. This one should be a little bit nicer, too, for the sake of the video. It's got a louder exhaust, which I think will make it easier to hear exactly what's going on with the engine. I gotta tell you,
Speaker 6 (lower-pitched voice): Driving stick is just fun, okay? There's times when it's a little bit of pain in the butt. You know, if you're in LA traffic, obviously if you're in New York, maybe not the most fun thing in the world, especially you got a heavy clutch and it can get really old sitting there for a long time in traffic. But for
the
Speaker 4: majority of driving, having just a cool sports car that you like with a good stick
shift,
Speaker 4: Good transmission, it's very enjoyable.
Speaker 6 (lower-pitched voice): It makes driving a lot more fun and frankly keeps me more into the moment and being a safer driver 'cause I'm more well connected. I also find I don't get as bored as easily driving so I think I end up being safer and staying awake more. And lastly, with a stick shift, it's a little easier to tell how fast you're going so it makes it
Speaker 6 (lower-pitched voice): easier to have fun and
Man 5: not necessarily get busted for speeding because i find automatic cars or sports cars so boring you have to speed like crazy to have any fun and then that doesn't help your driver's license or your wallet getting tickets so down to shifting i want to talk about it now the biggest thing for young people is getting going just starting from a dead stop so right now we're
on level
Man 5: level ground, I don't have to worry about rolling backwards if you're going up a hill, that's something else to talk about and you can use a parking brake for assistance with that. But right now I'm sitting in traffic, I've got my foot off the clutch and
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): it's in neutral. So I'm pushing the clutch, engage first, I'm not gonna rip it in, I'm not gonna jam it in, I'm just gonna put it in with
Speaker 6 (lower-pitched voice): what the gearbox wants. You gotta kinda be nice to it, firmly do the actions you need and make it happen. And when you pull away from the traffic light,
Speaker 6 (lower-pitched voice): You don't need to rev the heck out of it and then slip the clutch for a long period of time
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): that's over wearing it. But you also don't want to do it super low end, start letting the clutch out that the engine bogs or stall. So as a general rule of thumb,
Speaker 6 (lower-pitched voice): when you pull away from either a stop light or a stop sign, you're only going to use the amount of RPM.
Speaker 6 (lower-pitched voice): the engine or the amount of power that you need to take off and as you get better and better you'll be able to use less if
Man 5: that makes sense now it'll be another video where I'm going to talk about doing things like hole shots and I've got other videos relating to shifting
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): and downshifting and upshifting all that but I really just wanted to go over the basics so in coming up to a stop line like I just did here
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): some other young people have asked me relating to it. Do you just push it neutral, or excuse me, push in the clutch and just like coast up with the engine going back to idle and breaking? Or do you downshift, you know, like you're in a motorcycle or in a race car? Or if you're driving along at 55 miles an hour, do you just push in the clutch, stick it in first gear until you get there?
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): All right, well the last one, don't do that. One of the fastest ways to wear out a gearbox and just screw it up and destroy the synchros is, people who literally will be driving down the road at 55 miles an hour, they know they've got a 90 degree corner coming up, which in general in cars is a second gear corner. So they'll push in the clutch and just jam it in second, even though the car is still doing like
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): 50 miles an hour, they'll break up to it and make the turn, then let out the clutch and
go.
You
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): don't want to do that, because what's happening is, in a gearbox, when you're moving down the road and your tires are spinning,
parts of the
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): internals of the gearbox are
Speaker 6 (lower-pitched voice): spinning the speed of the roadway. For instance, in the case of
the Porsche
Speaker 6 (lower-pitched voice): here, it has a transaxle, so the ring and pinion, which drives the shafts to the wheels, is in the transmission.
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): And those are directly connected to a lot of the gears and spinning in the case of a front engine car a typical one where the gearbox is up There and the
Speaker 6 (lower-pitched voice): trans trans excuse me the differential is in the back That's still happening because that drive shaft there is always spinning so I'm going on a little bit longer But you need to be selecting gears that relate to how fast you're actually going So if you're pulling up to us if you're coming up to a stop
and
Speaker 6 (lower-pitched voice): or you're coming up to a slow corner, you don't just push in the clutch immediately
Man 5: and jam it in that low gear that you need. You need to wait, okay? So as one example, like I got to slow down, I got slow traffic. I will literally just take my foot off the brake or take my foot off the gas, I'm in fifth gear right now, and I'll just start gently braking with it in
gear.
And
Man 7: that's effectively engine braking for just normal driving. Sorry, I'm actually in traffic
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): so I can't demonstrate perfectly right now. But if you're leaving it in, say, the gear that you're in, the RPM are coming down. And maybe when you get to 1500
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): RPM, that's when you push in the clutch and let it go to idle.
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): But if you wait too long and you come to a stop or right before you come to a stop and your car starts shuttering, that's because with the clutch out and it in gear, you have a direct mechanical connection from the engine
Man 7: to the transmission, to your differential, to your wheels. So you will stall or start bucking your engine. So
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): you know, if I'm slowing down and it's still in a top gear and I'm coming to a stop, stop sign, stop light, whatever.
The
Man 5: laziest, easiest thing to do, just normal driving is just leave it in the gear you were in, start, you know, let off the, you know, gas, the car starts engine braking a little and slowing down, and then you can just gently brake until you get to where you're at, and then when you slow down enough, you push in the clutch, just like that, okay? And I got to stop the light coming up here, but I just wanted to
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): illustrate that while I was still yapping.
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): Now the other thing that you'll see me doing is if it's a long way to go, I downshifted in a fourth and now I'm kind of downshifting in a
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): third. I
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): don't need to do that.
Man 5: It was a little bit of fun. The other thing too is if you have a stop light that's there and you don't necessarily know when it's going to turn
green,
If you
Man 5: just leave it in fifth gear and you're slowing down, and now let's say you're doing 20 miles an hour and you think you're gonna stop, but all of a sudden it turns green and everybody needs to go, now suddenly you need to downshift to either probably second or third gear so that you can accelerate with traffic and go.
Man 5: leave it in fifth, then you're not really ready for it. So there's times like in traffic where you'll want to downshift and start selecting gears that are more appropriate for the slower speed you're going so that you then can take off.
Man 5: As another note I want to mention, you see me idling here at this
Speaker 6 (lower-pitched voice): stoplight and I put it in neutral and let the clutch out. There is a lot of talk and argument on do you just keep holding the clutch in if you're at a light or do you put it in neutral and let the clutch out? Well, I'll answer that by saying it's a judgment call. Now, the reason why there's a judgment
Man 5: call there is it has to do with wear on your car.
Man 5: and most specifically, the throwout bearing. So when you push in the clutch pedal, there is
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): either a mechanical connection via rods or cables to something called a fork that pushes a bearing that pushes in the diaphragm on the
Man 5: clutch and that's what physically disengages it, okay? Or of course you have a hydraulic master and slave cylinder, which is not PC. We'll probably end up having to change those names one day.
Speaker 6 (lower-pitched voice): to push in your throw out bearing. So that throw out
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): bearing, when it is pushing in the clutch diaphragm, it is spinning at engine RPM. So every time you push in that clutch, that bearing is moving. And,
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): In, I would say
Man 5: most cars, I know there are some that aren't like this, I can't really think which one's off the top of my head. But in most cars, the throwout bearing is not touching the clutch at all times. So when I have the clutch out, that throwout bearing is here, and let's say this is the clutch, it's just spinning and spinning and spinning. The throwout bearing is not, because every time you push it, you're putting a lot of force in it, it's spinning, you're wearing it.
Man 5: So, if I just sat here with my foot on the clutch, I would be wearing my throwout bearing and pushing the clutch and wearing all those linkages and I don't have to. And I know this light is going to take a little while and I don't really feel like pushing it in, so I'm just waiting.
You
Man 5: want to be a little more attentive if you're not in gear or, I don't know, there's people chasing you or you're about to get carjacked and you want to get out of here or something, you know what I mean? So you might want to be in gear if you think you're going to have to go real quickly, but I would say if you're going to be waiting enough time that it seems silly that you still have your foot on the clutch,
Man 5: you're pushing it in, then you probably want to think ahead and shift it into neutral, make sure you're neutral, let the clutch
Speaker 8: out reasonably. So that's just a little bit of an example there. Now, the other thing relating to
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): driving stick shift, which frankly makes people a much better driver, and is paramount if you're going to become a racing driver or sports car driver, is with the stick shift, you have a direct mechanical connection from the engine to the wheels.
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): So if you're in first or second gear, such
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): as when I went around that corner, if you let off the gas, it'll start engine braking. The engine wants to slow down. It's a big
Man 5: unit and it's trying to make the car slow down. And if I get on the throttle, I'll accelerate. Now that's, you're thinking, Casey, that's, well, duh. I mean, I knew that, but there's a difference. And a true automatic
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): transmission,
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): effectively has a fluid coupling. Now I know there's a lot of variations of that and you guys are gonna comment. However,
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): an automatic transmission coasts more. So you can be a lot dumber with your foot on an automatic car and it feels smooth. Whereas on a stick shift car, you have to be smooth and maintain positions and pedal pressure to continue that flow.
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): So I'll give an example, and there's people around there who probably think I'm a horrible driver if I do this. For young people, if you're pulling away from a stoplight, or let's say you're in a parking lot and your car starts to buck. If you whip on and off the gas, let's see if I can
do it. Oh yeah,
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): there it is. Oh God, I look like an idiot. You ever done that? Okay.
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): well that's what i mean about that smooth foot control so you're pushing the gas you know just a little bit like this and you're rolling
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): off off the clutch like this to accelerate and you're holding it right
if you
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): just go ahead and whip off the
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): gas and then back on like like basically a nervous new driver in a stick shift car you're going to cause a degrading oscillation in the drivetrain
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): And effectively,
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): the gearbox, the drive shaft, the half shafts that go to the wheels, they're all made of metal, and metal are different kinds of springs. And I know that sounds silly, but you start feeling like you're on the end of a spring for a reason. That's what's happening effectively.
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): So if you bounce a spring like this right if you've
Speaker 6 (lower-pitched voice): got a spring with a little weight at the end and you get it going Bouncing up and down. What do you do to stop it? You have to smooth it out and be real smooth with how you hold the spring with the weight and driving a car is exactly the same way with the throttle and that
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): goes on
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): for any kind of gear, which is also a hugely important tip for driving high horsepower, high torque cars, most especially like my Dodge Viper or the V12 Aston Martin, the old stick shift
Speaker 6 (lower-pitched voice): one. When you've got a high horsepower car, you now have the ability for just with your throttle
to
Speaker 6 (lower-pitched voice): break the tires loose from adhesion. The engine makes so much power that you can just spin the tires at
Man 5: will at a lot of time, which you don't wanna do, so in that circumstance, you have to be thinking of the traction of the tires, but also maintaining a very smooth on your throttle. And I'm going on a big tangent here, but in the sake of power sliding higher horsepower cars,
Man 5: one of the biggest mistakes that people
Man 7: do when they're learning to power slide is they get nervous and let off the gas early then the car bites and hooks and then it gets ugly and bad
Man 5: things happen where it's sort of like you got to stay in the gas but not too much and hold it and keep the spin going to be smooth so even doing things like that require a certain decisive confidence and smoothness so
Man 5: Where I'm going with this is, guys, just the basics here. Driving stick shift, super fun, super rewarding. And actually with older cars, stick shift cars get better fuel mileage than do automatics. They have less drag, so that's kind of a plus. And in the older days, before dual sequential clutches and all kinds of fancy automatics that shift real fast and everything, stick shift cars were faster accelerating than an automatic, generally
Speaker 6 (lower-pitched voice): speaking. And they're just way more
fun.
there's a
Speaker 6 (lower-pitched voice): lot of value to having a car like this but the biggest tip I can give you is if you you need to understand
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): what's happening when you are driving a car like what what are the controls do what what's actually happening going on here because if
Speaker 6 (lower-pitched voice): you feel a clunk or a deceleration or something like that you really
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): just need to think about it
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): and you will be able to self-diagnose what you've done wrong or what you could do better. All right, so if when you're first learning to change gears and you are upshifting, if when you change
Speaker 6 (lower-pitched voice): gears, there's a slight deceleration right before you go,
Speaker 6 (lower-pitched voice): Well that means that you let off the gas first, then pushed in the clutch. So you need to push in the clutch a little sooner in the timing. And the reason it decelerates
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): is because you let off the gas for a second before you let in the clutch. And that's why that can get jerky. Or the other way around, if all of a sudden when you shift gears there's an acceleration burst like this.
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): That's because you didn't
Speaker 6 (lower-pitched voice): let off the gas enough for the RPM to come down, you held it up there and you just let out the clutch and that's effectively like popping
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): the clutch you know when you're going to launch a car from a dead stop and that's why you might get a sudden acceleration force like that. But those are just real basic things that you can self-diagnose when you're driving a car and one of the other nice things about a stick
shift is it's
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): hard to keep driving the car badly.
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): unless you're just clueless with what's going on because a stick shift car will tell you what you're doing wrong so if it seems wrong it probably is and as a note your actions the amount of rpms you use the amount of shifting really just comes down to what is the most efficient way to get the job done if you're slipping the clutch a long way and you're really revving it up and and everything, and you don't need to do that.
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): That's not efficient, so don't do that as much. Or if the car is dying and you need a little more, do it. Just vibe with the car and it will literally tell you what it needs. And then of course
Man 5: when you can become proficient enough at driving like that, that's when you start getting into little better techniques like
Speaker 6 (lower-pitched voice): downshifting at speed, toe heel downshifting. You guys really don't need to worry
Man 5: about double clutching or single clutching, that
means
Man 5: When you push in the clutch one time to shift, that's single clutching. You push the clutch in twice, that's called double clutching. We're not going to talk about that right now. That has everything to do with synchronizing the speed of the transmission to the next gear you're going to be in. Not really necessary in a modern
Speaker 6 (lower-pitched voice): synchronized mesh box. As another note, I want to say something else for all the trolls out there that saw me put my hand in like this.
Speaker 6 (lower-pitched voice): and turn like this from the
Man 5: dead stop. I well realize that every single racing instructor on the planet as well as every single driver's out on the planet tell you not to do that for a multitude of reasons. One of which if you do this and the airbag goes off, it breaks your arm and sticks your
arm in your
Man 5: face. And the biggest one is it's not efficient. But the reason I did it is because this car has no power steering and I was at a dead stop so I needed the extra
Man 5: leverage for a moment to drive it. Yeah, sure I could do that, but no. There are certain circumstances, for instance that, where it's acceptable to do the arm hook type thing just once, so I just wanted to say that because I know there's gonna be about a million people say that and it's really
annoying.
I
Man 5: realize you drive a really fancy new car with really great power steering, but not everybody has that. But I will say this, that is a terrible thing to do when you're actually driving and moving on the road. When the car is actually moving, it is easier to steer. You guys probably know that, especially everybody who ever has a non-power steering car. But for instance, right now, if I needed to turn, it's harder for me to turn the wheel
Man 5: to go like that. So I may just hook it from a dead stop if the power steering isn't so great. And actually now that I think of it, I'm full of crap. I forgot this car actually does have power steering. It's not over boosted. My other 944 didn't have it. So maybe
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): I'm just being a
wuss.
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): Anyway guys, I hope this is a little bit helpful for you new drivers out there, share it with anybody,
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): but basically, let the car talk to you and be efficient, but driving a manual transmission is a heck of a lot of fun, and nowadays, if you can find them, a lot of people can't drive stick. So sometimes you get a really good smoking deal on a manual transmission car, you'll find it's better fuel efficiency, more fun to drive, and you might be
Speaker 6 (lower-pitched voice): able to just get one cheaper.
Speaker 6 (lower-pitched voice): And I like all of those things. So you're gonna have a lot of fun. Let it talk to you. I've got some other videos on shifting, clutches, and braking. Check those out. Please comment below with things you might like to see, and I look forward to doing another video in the future. Of course, subscribe. We've got a lot of amazing builds coming up with supercars, race cars, racing adventures, and of course, fun tips like this now and then. So please subscribe,
Speaker 9: click that bell,
Speaker 9: and I look forward to see you next time.
Speaker 10: Very cool thing happening right now at the Packard American Motor Company. They're debuting their very first watch. This is the 1899 Model A. It's a mechanical automatic movement with a beautiful stainless steel case. All the parts are made in Switzerland. It's assembled right here in the United States. If you happen to have a Packard, you can get your serial number engraved right on it.
Speaker 10: But you guys need to go to PackardAmerica.us. This particular watch is mine. I'm looking very forward to wearing it more. It's
Speaker 4: frankly very comfortable. One of the best watches I've ever had. But this one's mine, not yours. You can't have it. Get your own. PackardAmerica.us.